Autoreg Pro has been updated to version 3.68. There are many improvements, but the most exciting one is the new automatic skirt setup.
AutoRig Pro가 3.68 버전으로 업데이트됐어요. 개선점이 많은데, 그중 가장 흥미로운 건 새로운 자동 스커트 셋업이에요.
So in this video, we'll focus on the skirt rig. I'll show you how to set it up and how to use it. It is very easy.
이번 영상에서는 스커트 리그에 집중할게요. 설정 방법과 사용법을 보여드릴게요. 아주 간단해요.
In fact, I would say that this is the easiest way to create a bone rig for a skirt in Blender.
사실 블렌더에서 스커트용 본 리그를 만드는 가장 쉬운 방법이라고 말할 수 있어요.
If you're interested in the other new features, you can find out all of them on the official Autoreg Pro documentation page.
다른 신기능이 궁금하시다면 AutoRig Pro 공식 문서 페이지에서 모두 확인하실 수 있어요.
So here is my character model wearing a skirt. I have the skirt as a separate object.
여기 스커트를 입은 제 캐릭터 모델이 있어요. 스커트는 별도의 오브젝트로 분리해 두었어요.
You can join them into a single object if you prefer, but this just makes my life a little bit easier.
원하시면 하나의 오브젝트로 합쳐도 되지만, 저는 이렇게 하는 게 작업이 좀 더 편하더라고요.
For the basic human rig, I'm going to select the character, expand the end panel, go to ARP, and go to the Smart Features,
기본 인간 리그를 위해 캐릭터를 선택하고, N 패널을 펼쳐 ARP로 가서 Smart Features로 이동하겠습니다,
Get Selected Objects, and press OK.
'Get Selected Objects'를 누르고 OK를 눌러요.
Then, as usual, I'll add the neck, chin, shoulders, and so on.
그다음 평소처럼 목, 턱, 어깨 등등을 추가해 줄게요.
And press Go.
그리고 Go를 누릅니다.
At this point, you should check your fingers alignment.
이 시점에서 손가락 정렬을 확인해야 해요.
I can play around with the settings for the automatic finger alignment,
자동 손가락 정렬 설정을 조절할 수도 있고,
or I can just align the fingers manually as I'm doing right now.
지금처럼 손가락을 수동으로 정렬해도 돼요.
Now, I can press Much To Rig.
이제 'Match to Rig'를 누르면 돼요.
So we are here for the skirt, so let's see how we can add the skirt setup to this rig.
우리는 스커트를 보러 왔으니, 이 리그에 스커트 셋업을 어떻게 추가하는지 보죠.
If I click on Add Limb at the bottom, you'll see Clothes, Kilt.
아래쪽의 Add Limb을 클릭하면 Clothes, Kilt가 보여요.
So I'll go to Edit Reference Bones, and add the kilt setup.
그래서 Edit Reference Bones로 가서 Kilt 셋업을 추가할게요.
And right away, this gives me these bones arranged kind of like a skirt.
그러면 바로 스커트처럼 배열된 본들이 생깁니다.
Now, normally, in Edit Reference Bones, you won't go to Pose Mode, but just for a second, I'm going to go to Pose Mode.
보통 Edit Reference Bones에서는 포즈 모드로 가지 않지만, 잠깐만 포즈 모드로 가볼게요.
So we have this Master Bone, and if we move it around in Pose Mode, you'll see that all of the skirt bones are parented to it.
여기 마스터 본이 있고, 포즈 모드에서 움직여 보면 모든 스커트 본이 여기에 부모 연결되어 있는 걸 볼 수 있어요.
And also, the Master Skirt Bone is parented to the bottom spine bone.
또한 스커트 마스터 본은 하단 척추 본에 부모 연결되어 있어요.
Autoretic Pro just assumed that I would like to parent the skirt to the waist of the character.
AutoRig Pro가 스커트를 캐릭터의 허리에 부모로 연결하길 원한다고 가정해 자동으로 그렇게 해 준 거죠.
So it does this automatically, but if you wanted to parent the skirt to another spine bone, you can go to Edit Mode, select your Skirt Master,
그래서 자동으로 이렇게 처리해 주지만, 스커트를 다른 척추 본에 부모 연결하고 싶다면 Edit 모드로 가서 Skirt Master를 선택하고,
Shift-Select the spine bone that you want to parent to, and then just press Ctrl-P and Keep Offset.
부모로 삼을 척추 본을 Shift로 함께 선택한 다음, Ctrl+P를 눌러 'Keep Offset'을 선택하면 됩니다.
I'm not going to do this here because I'm happy with my parenting.
저는 지금 이 부모 설정이 마음에 들어서 여기서는 바꾸지 않을게요.
The next step is to align the skirt bones.
다음 단계는 스커트 본을 정렬하는 거예요.
I'm going to place the Skirt Master in the middle of the body.
Skirt Master를 몸의 중앙 쪽에 배치하겠습니다.
Then go to the Armature tab, Viewport Display, and switch the display to Stick.
그다음 Armature 탭의 Viewport Display에서 표시 방식을 Stick으로 바꿔요.
I find that this makes it much easier to align the skirt bones.
이렇게 하면 스커트 본을 정렬하기가 훨씬 쉬워지더라고요.
And in this case, having In Front Enabled is a little bit confusing, so I'm going to turn it off.
이 경우 'In Front'를 켜두면 좀 헷갈리니 끄겠습니다.
And now, I can start moving these bones.
이제 이 본들을 움직이기 시작할 수 있어요.
So, I want to align the top of each bone with the top of the skirt, and the bottom of each bone to the bottom of the skirt.
각 본의 위쪽은 스커트 윗단에, 아래쪽은 스커트 아랫단에 맞춰 정렬하고 싶어요.
To do so, I'm going to switch to Face Project, and then just grab one bone end, hold Ctrl, and snap it to the surface of the skirt.
그러려면 Face Project로 전환하고, 본 끝을 하나 잡은 다음 Ctrl을 누른 채 스커트 표면에 스냅해 줍니다.
Then grab the other end, and snap it to the bottom of the skirt.
그다음 반대쪽 끝도 잡아서 스커트 아랫단에 스냅해요.
And I'll just keep doing that for all bones.
이 작업을 모든 본에 대해 반복하면 됩니다.
I have X Mirroring enabled, so I only have to do one side.
저는 X 미러링을 켜 두었기 때문에 한쪽만 하면 돼요.
Once I have the bones aligned, I can go to AutoRig Pro again, and match the rig.
본 정렬이 끝나면 AutoRig Pro로 돌아가서 다시 Match to Rig를 합니다.
And now you'll see that we have some skirt bones.
이제 스커트 본들이 생긴 걸 볼 수 있어요.
So, to see how they work, let's do a quick skinning.
어떻게 동작하는지 보기 위해 빠르게 스키닝을 해 봅시다.
I'll select the body, and skirt, and then shift select the rig, go to Skin.
바디와 스커트를 선택하고, 리그를 Shift로 추가 선택한 다음 Skin으로 가요.
And with these default options, I'm going to click Bind.
기본 옵션 그대로 Bind를 클릭하겠습니다.
Now, if I move the leg of the character, you'll see that it is just poking through a skirt, and nothing is happening.
이제 캐릭터의 다리를 움직여 보면 스커트를 그냥 뚫고 지나가고, 아무 일도 일어나지 않죠.
I can grab one of these skirt controllers, and manually rotate it, but that is not what we want.
이 스커트 컨트롤러 중 하나를 잡아서 수동으로 회전시킬 수는 있지만, 우리가 원하는 건 그게 아니에요.
We want automation. So, let's set it up.
우리는 자동화를 원하죠. 셋업해 봅시다.
Go back to Rig, Edit Reference Bones.
Rig로 돌아가서 Edit Reference Bones로 갑니다.
And now, if I select the kilt master bone, or any of the individual skirt bones, the limb options button will become active.
이제 Kilt 마스터 본이나 개별 스커트 본을 선택하면 Limb Options 버튼이 활성화돼요.
And if I click on it, I'll get all of the options that are related to the skirt rig.
그걸 클릭하면 스커트 리그와 관련된 모든 옵션을 볼 수 있어요.
And I'm going to explain all of these settings, but first, let's set up the automation, or the collision.
이 설정들을 모두 설명하겠지만, 먼저 자동화, 즉 충돌 설정부터 해 봅시다.
To set it up, you need to specify the leg left and leg right fields.
설정하려면 왼쪽 다리와 오른쪽 다리 필드를 지정해야 해요.
For the standard OuterRig Pro rig, you have to start typing thigh, and for the left leg, choose thigh L.
표준 AutoRig Pro 리그에서는 'thigh'를 입력하기 시작하고, 왼쪽 다리는 'thigh.L'을 선택하세요.
And then thigh R for the right leg.
오른쪽 다리는 'thigh.R'을 선택합니다.
Press OK. Match the rig.
OK를 누르고, Match to Rig를 해요.
And now, if I try to move the leg, you'll see that something is happening.
이제 다리를 움직여 보면 뭔가 반응하는 걸 볼 수 있어요.
We still have a lot of overlap between the leg and the skirt.
그래도 다리와 스커트가 많이 겹치죠.
If I select one of the skirt bones, and go to Tool, here we have rig settings, which we can tweak and change the behavior of the rig on the fly.
스커트 본 중 하나를 선택하고 Tool로 가면 리그 설정이 있는데, 여기서 즉석으로 값을 조정해 리그 동작을 바꿀 수 있어요.
And because I have a skirt bone selected, I have rig settings related to the skirt.
지금 스커트 본을 선택했기 때문에 스커트 관련 리그 설정이 보입니다.
The first setting is Collide, and it goes from 1 to 0.
첫 번째 설정은 Collide이고, 1에서 0까지로 조절해요.
0 simply means off. That will be the same as having no automation.
0은 꺼짐을 의미해요. 즉 자동화가 없는 것과 같죠.
So just keep it to 1.
그래서 1로 두면 됩니다.
The next setting is one of the most important ones.
다음 설정이 가장 중요한 것 중 하나예요.
If you increase it, you'll see that the skirt will start covering the leg.
값을 올리면 스커트가 다리를 가리기 시작하는 걸 볼 수 있어요.
Collide Distance is basically the distance between each bone and the leg that affects it.
Collide Distance는 기본적으로 각 본과 그에 영향을 주는 다리 사이의 거리예요.
If you increase this too much, you'll see that some bones start being affected, even though the leg is not even moved.
이 값을 너무 크게 하면 다리가 움직이지 않았는데도 일부 본이 영향을 받기 시작해요.
So that is too much. I'm going to undo.
그건 과해요. 되돌리겠습니다.
The next setting I'm going to skip for a second, and then Collide Spread.
다음 설정은 잠시 건너뛰고, Collide Spread를 볼게요.
If you increase it, you'll notice that more and more skirt bones are being affected.
이 값을 올리면 더 많은 스커트 본이 영향을 받는 걸 알 수 있어요.
And this setting is also very important when trying to make this setup as automated as possible.
이 셋업을 최대한 자동화하려고 할 때 이 설정도 매우 중요해요.
On this one too, if you push it too far, it starts getting weird.
이것도 너무 과하게 올리면 이상해지기 시작합니다.
So be careful with it. And just increase it as much as needed.
그러니 주의해서, 필요한 만큼만 올리세요.
This setup is not meant to be perfect.
이 셋업은 완벽함을 목표로 하지는 않아요.
So at some point, at some extreme angle, the leg will poke through the skirt.
어느 순간, 극단적인 각도에서는 다리가 스커트를 뚫고 나올 거예요.
In these cases, you can improve this manually.
이런 경우에는 수동으로 보정하시면 돼요.
So my point is, don't try to make this completely automatic.
그러니까 제 말은, 이걸 100% 자동으로 만들려고 하지 마세요.
That may be a waste of time.
그건 시간 낭비일 수 있어요.
The best approach, in my opinion, is to make it as automatic as possible,
제 생각에 가장 좋은 접근은 가능한 한 자동화하되,
but don't think that something is wrong just because you have to make some manual tweaks here and there.
중간중간 수동으로 약간 손봐야 한다고 해서 문제가 있다고 생각하진 마세요.
The ideal animation workflow is to just animate your main bones, your legs,
이상적인 애니메이션 워크플로는 다리 같은 주요 본만 먼저 애니메이션하고,
and then as a second animation pass, come through and manually fix any intersections between the legs and the cloth that you can find.
두 번째 패스로 돌아와 다리와 옷 사이의 겹침을 눈에 보이는 대로 수동으로 고치는 거예요.
And finally, we have this Collide Falloff setting.
마지막으로 Collide Falloff 설정이 있어요.
Unlike the other settings, I find it a little bit unintuitive,
다른 설정들과 달리 약간은 직관적이지 않다고 느끼지만,
but it will also increase or decrease the automation effect.
이것도 자동화 효과를 높이거나 낮출 수 있어요.
So play with it and see what works.
직접 조절해 보면서 본인에게 맞는 값을 찾으세요.
By the way, you also have this Master Control,
참고로, 이런 마스터 컨트롤도 있어요,
which can be used to move the whole skirt around.
이건 스커트 전체를 한꺼번에 움직일 때 쓸 수 있어요.
So these are the basics, but we can go a little bit deeper.
기본은 이렇고, 이제 조금 더 깊게 들어가 볼게요.
If I go to ARP and Edit Reference Bones,
ARP의 Edit Reference Bones로 가서,
select one of the skirt bones and again, Limb Options.
스커트 본 하나를 선택하고, 다시 Limb Options를 엽니다.
Let's see what other options we have here.
여기에 어떤 다른 옵션이 있는지 볼게요.
So first of all, we have Count Per Side.
먼저 'Count Per Side'가 있어요.
And it was set to 6.
지금은 6으로 설정되어 있죠.
And if I count the number of skirt bones, you'll find out that there are 12.
스커트 본 개수를 세어 보면 12개예요.
So 6 on each side.
즉 한쪽에 6개씩이죠.
So this setting here will set how many skirt bones we have.
이 설정으로 스커트 본 개수를 정할 수 있어요.
We can go as low as 3 or as high as 128, which will be a little bit crazy.
최소 3부터 최대 128까지 가능하고, 128은 꽤 과하죠.
I'm going to set it to 4 for a second and press OK just to see the effect.
효과를 보기 위해 잠깐 4로 바꾸고 OK를 눌러볼게요.
And you'll see that now I have 8 skirt bones.
이제 스커트 본이 8개가 된 걸 볼 수 있어요.
Now, if I move some of them around a little bit and then go back to the Limb Options,
이제 몇 개를 조금 움직여 보고 Limb Options로 다시 돌아가면,
you'll see this Preserve Shape setting.
'Preserve Shape'라는 설정이 보일 거예요.
So if I change the count to 6, let's say, and have Preserve Shape on,
여기서 예를 들어 개수를 6으로 바꾸고 Preserve Shape를 켠 상태라면,
you'll see that Autoric Pro tried to respect these changes to the bones that I did when I had 4 bones.
AutoRig Pro가 4개였을 때 제가 본에 준 변경을 가능한 한 유지하려고 시도한 걸 볼 수 있어요.
Whereas, if I disable this and change the count, it will completely reset the shape of the bones,
반면 이걸 끄고 개수를 바꾸면 본 모양이 완전히 리셋돼요,
which may be what you want when you make changes.
변경할 때 그게 원하는 동작일 수도 있죠.
I was happy with the previous setup, so I'll try to undo.
저는 이전 셋업이 더 마음에 들어서 되돌릴게요.
Here I have my 6 bones.
다시 6개의 본이 준비됐어요.
So let's see what other options we have.
다른 옵션도 계속 살펴볼게요.
There are Master Controllers, so let's enable them.
마스터 컨트롤러가 있으니 켜 보겠습니다.
Press OK.
OK를 눌러요.
And now, aside from the green controls, we have new red controls.
이제 초록 컨트롤 외에 빨간 컨트롤도 생겼어요.
And they control not just one bone, but a couple of adjacent bones.
이 컨트롤은 한 개 본이 아니라 인접한 여러 본을 함께 제어합니다.
So these Master Controllers can make your life a little bit easier.
그래서 마스터 컨트롤러가 작업을 조금 더 쉽게 해줘요.
Instead of rotating one bone at a time, you can affect multiple bones and work faster.
본을 하나씩 돌리는 대신 여러 본에 동시에 영향을 주며 더 빨리 작업할 수 있죠.
Let's go back to Edit Reference Bones.
다시 Edit Reference Bones로 돌아갑시다.
Limb Options.
Limb Options.
And so, here we have Master Frequency.
여기에는 'Master Frequency'가 있어요.
Actually, it seems like my count is set to 4, so let's set it to 6 again.
카운트가 4로 되어 있네요, 다시 6으로 바꿀게요.
And go back to Limb Options.
그리고 다시 Limb Options로 돌아가요.
So Master Frequency set to 2 means that for every two individual bones, I'll have one Master Control.
Master Frequency가 2면 개별 본 두 개마다 마스터 컨트롤 하나가 생긴다는 뜻이에요.
If you want to have less, you can increase this number.
마스터 컨트롤 수를 줄이고 싶다면 이 수치를 올리면 돼요.
Next, we have Subdivision, and that will give you more control in your final rig.
다음은 'Subdivision'인데, 최종 리그에서 더 많은 컨트롤을 제공합니다.
So let's set Subdivision to 2, and press OK.
Subdivision을 2로 설정하고 OK를 눌러요.
And match the rig.
그다음 Match to Rig를 합니다.
And you'll see that we have additional skirt bones.
그러면 스커트 본이 추가된 걸 볼 수 있어요.
These additional bones do not affect the skirt.
이 추가 본들은 아직 스커트에 영향을 주지 않아요.
So I have to select the meshes, Shift-select the rig, skin, and just bind again.
그래서 메시들을 선택하고, 리그를 Shift로 추가 선택해 Skin으로 가서 다시 바인드해야 해요.
And now I have these additional skirt bones, which will give me even more control over the skirt.
이제 추가된 스커트 본 덕분에 스커트를 더 세밀하게 제어할 수 있게 됐어요.
And I also have Master Controllers on each row.
각 행마다 마스터 컨트롤러도 생겼고요.
OK.
좋아요.
Let's go back to Edit Reference Bones.
Edit Reference Bones로 다시 갑시다.
Limb Options.
Limb Options.
So if I have a subdivision of 3, and match the rig, I'll have 3 rows.
Subdivision을 3으로 하면, Match to Rig 후에 3개의 행을 얻게 됩니다.
And I'll have to skin things again.
그리고 다시 스키닝을 해야겠죠.
But that gives me even more control.
하지만 그만큼 더 많은 컨트롤을 제공합니다.
Next, we have the option to subdivide the reference bones.
다음으로, 레퍼런스 본 자체를 세분화하는 옵션이 있어요.
If I keep this unchecked, even though I have 3 subdivisions for each bone, in reference bones mode, I have a single bone for each skirt segment.
이걸 체크 해제해 두면 각 본의 세분 수가 3이어도, 레퍼런스 본 모드에서는 스커트 조각마다 본이 하나만 보여요.
And that just makes it much easier to align the bones.
그렇게 하면 본 정렬이 훨씬 쉬워집니다.
But if you prefer to have more control, you can choose to subdivide the reference bones.
하지만 더 세밀한 제어를 원한다면 레퍼런스 본을 세분화하도록 선택할 수 있어요.
Press OK.
OK를 누릅니다.
And you'll see that now each skirt segment consists of 3 bones.
그러면 이제 각 스커트 조각이 3개의 본으로 구성된 걸 볼 수 있어요.
So, if you have a skirt with a weird shape, you'll be able to align your bones to it exactly as you want.
따라서 형태가 특이한 스커트라면 원하는 대로 본을 더 정확히 맞출 수 있죠.
So, I'm going to set subdivision to 2, with subdivide reference bones.
저는 레퍼런스 본 세분화를 켠 채 Subdivision을 2로 설정하겠습니다.
Just to make it a little bit more manageable.
관리하기 조금 더 수월하도록요.
And then I'll align these bones.
그리고 이 본들을 정렬할게요.
Just like before, using face snapping.
아까처럼 페이스 스내핑을 사용해서요.
Match the rig.
Match to Rig.
Then I'm going to reskin just for good measure.
그다음 확실히 하려고 다시 스키닝하겠습니다.
Right.
좋습니다.
Let's take a look at the remaining settings.
이제 남은 설정들을 살펴볼게요.
The master controller's row setting.
마스터 컨트롤러의 Row 설정이에요.
If we enable it, then press OK.
이걸 켜고 OK를 누른 다음,
And match the rig.
Match to Rig를 하면,
Will give us additional master controllers.
마스터 컨트롤러가 추가로 생깁니다.
These big circular controllers control an entire row of the skirt.
이 큼직한 원형 컨트롤러는 스커트의 한 행 전체를 제어해요.
And that's all there is to it.
설정은 이게 전부예요.
It can be very useful.
상당히 유용할 수 있죠.
We also have this option for interactive collision distance.
또 'Interactive Collision Distance' 옵션이 있어요.
Which is on by default.
기본값으로 켜져 있습니다.
And I always keep it on.
저는 항상 켜둡니다.
Supposedly, if you turn it off, it will take away from the tweakability of the rig.
이걸 끄면 리그를 미세 조정하는 능력이 줄어든다고 해요.
But it would give you better performance.
대신 성능은 더 좋아질 수 있죠.
But the performance hit is not that big.
하지만 성능 하락이 크지 않아서,
And so, generally, I would keep this option on.
일반적으로는 이 옵션을 켜두는 편이 좋아요.
And finally, we have collide on Z.
마지막으로 'Collide on Z'가 있어요.
This is an additional option that will give you additional precision in the interaction between legs and skirt.
이건 다리와 스커트 사이의 상호작용을 좀 더 정밀하게 해 주는 추가 옵션이에요.
According to the manual, this option also has a little bit of a performance cost.
매뉴얼에 따르면 이 옵션도 약간의 성능 비용이 들어요.
In exchange, it creates better interaction, better automation.
대신 상호작용과 자동화 품질이 더 좋아집니다.
And again, the performance cost is not something that you should worry about in general.
역시나 일반적으로 걱정할 정도의 성능 저하는 아니에요.
But if your PC is very slow, or if your scene is very heavy, then keep it off.
하지만 PC가 많이 느리거나 씬이 매우 무겁다면 꺼 두세요.
And finally, we have shapes.
마지막으로 Shapes 설정입니다.
With the scale slider, you can change the scale of these skirt controls.
Scale 슬라이더로 스커트 컨트롤의 크기를 바꿀 수 있어요.
And these options here will determine where the controls will appear.
여기 있는 옵션들은 컨트롤이 어디에 나타날지를 결정해요.
Currently, the option is set to tail, which means that controls will appear at the end of the bones.
현재는 'Tail'로 되어 있어서, 컨트롤이 본의 끝부분에 나타납니다.
But you can switch it to head, which means at the beginning of the bone.
하지만 'Head'로 바꾸면 본의 시작점에,
Or middle, which means in the middle of the bone.
혹은 'Middle'로 바꾸면 본의 중간에 나타나요.
Let's set it to middle.
여기서는 Middle로 설정해 보죠.
So it should appear here, and here, and here, and so on.
그럼 컨트롤이 여기, 그리고 여기, 이런 식으로 중간에 나타나야 해요.
Match to rig.
Match to Rig.
And that is exactly where the controls appear.
컨트롤이 정확히 그 위치에 나타났죠.
And that's all about the new skirt rig in AutoRig Pro.
AutoRig Pro의 새로운 스커트 리그에 대한 내용은 여기까지예요.
Enjoy and happy rigging.
즐겁게 작업하시고, 해피 리깅 되세요.